<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="no"?>
<ViewContext version="1.0.0"
             id="mars"
             xmlns="http://www.opengis.net/context"
             xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
             xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
             xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.opengis.net/context http://schemas.opengis.net/context/1.0.0/context.xsd">
	<General>
		<Window width="500" height="250"/>
		<BoundingBox SRS="EPSG:4326" minx="-180" miny="-90" maxx="180" maxy="90"/>
		<Title>Mars</Title>
		<Abstract>This data product is a topographic map of Mars at a resolution of 0.00781 (1/128) by 0.00781 degrees, based on altimetry data acquired by the Mars Global Surveyor MOLA instrument and accumulated over the course of the primary and extended mission. The MOLA Precision Experiment Data Records (PEDRs) are the source for this data set. The map is in the form of a binary table with one row for each 0.00781-degree latitude. Map coordinates use the IAU2000 reference system, and areoid defined by the Goddard Mars potential model GMM3 (mgm1025) evaluated to degree and order 50. The binned data include all MOLA nadir observations from the Mapping Phase through the Primary and Extended missions, from the end of aerobraking in February 1999 through June 2001. Additionally, off-nadir observations of the north pole are included from 87 N latitude and northward, taken during the spring of 1998, and of both poles taken during Mapping from 87 N and S to the poles. Data are adjusted using a first-order crossover solution for radial, along-track, and across-track position. Parts of orbits are excluded where solutions for these orbits are deemed to be poor. (Note: subtract 10000 from a MOLA mapping phase orbit number to determine the equivalent MGS Project orbit number.) Also excluded are shots more than 1.2 degree off-nadir (except as noted above), channel 4 returns, and any returns not classified as ground returns, e.g. clouds or noise, according to the SHOT_CLASSIFICATION_CODE. A total of nearly 600,000,000 observations are represented.</Abstract>
	</General> 
	<LayerList>
		<Layer queryable="1" hidden="0">
			<Server service="OGC:WMS" version="1.1.1" title="OGC:WMS">
				<OnlineResource xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://demo.cubewerx.com/demo/cubeserv/cubeserv.cgi?CONFIG=mars"/>
			</Server>
			<Name>MOLA128:MARS_DATA</Name>
			<Title>Mars Topography</Title>
			<SRS>EPSG:4326</SRS>
			<FormatList>
				<Format current="1">image/png</Format>
			</FormatList>
			<StyleList>
				<Style current="1">
					<Name>Land%20Shade</Name>
					<Title>Land Shade</Title>
					<LegendURL width="16" height="16" format="image/gif">
						<OnlineResource xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://demo.cubewerx.com/demo/cubeserv/cubeserv.cgi?CONFIG=mars&amp;VERSION=1.1.1&amp;REQUEST=GetLegendGraphic&amp;LAYER=MOLA128%3AMARS_DATA&amp;STYLE=Land Shade&amp;FORMAT=image%2Fgif"/>
					</LegendURL>
				</Style>
			</StyleList>
		</Layer>
		<Layer queryable="1" hidden="1">
			<Server service="OGC:WMS" version="1.1.1" title="OGC:WMS">
				<OnlineResource xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://demo.cubewerx.com/demo/cubeserv/cubeserv.cgi?CONFIG=mars"/>
			</Server>
						<Name>SHADEDRED:MARS_DATA</Name>
						<Title>Shaded Red</Title>
						<Abstract>The Red Mars map is a 24bit colour image in Plate Carée Equirectangular projection, representing the surface of Mars, as viewable from space.  The new Mars colour was built using a mass of procedural textures for a seamless and distortion free pleasing look, and the remaining details were derived from  Nasa/Jpl* imagery.</Abstract>
			<SRS>EPSG:4326</SRS>
			<FormatList>
				<Format current="1">image/png</Format>
			</FormatList>
			<StyleList>
						<Style>
							<Name>default</Name>
							<Title>default</Title>
							<LegendURL width="16" height="16">
								<OnlineResource xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://demo.cubewerx.com/demo/cubeserv/cubeserv.cgi?CONFIG=mars&amp;SERVICE=WMS&amp;VERSION=1.1.1&amp;REQUEST=GetLegendGraphic&amp;LAYER=SHADEDRED%3AMARS_DATA&amp;FORMAT=image%2Fpng&amp;SIMPLE=TRUE"/>
							</LegendURL>
						</Style>
			</StyleList>
		</Layer>
		<Layer queryable="1" hidden="1">
			<Server service="OGC:WMS" version="1.1.1" title="OGC:WMS">
				<OnlineResource xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://demo.cubewerx.com/demo/cubeserv/cubeserv.cgi?CONFIG=mars"/>
			</Server>
						<Name>MDIM21:MARS_DATA</Name>
						<Title>Mars Global Digital Image Mosaic</Title>
						<Abstract> This layer is a global image map of Mars with a resolution of 256 pixels/degree (scale approximately 231 m/pixel at the equator). The black-and-white mosaic is processed to emphasize local topographic features. This mosaic, known as Mars Digital Image Model (MDIM) 2.1, replaces two earlier mosaics produced by the USGS from the same set of approximately 4600 Viking Orbiter images. The positional accuracy of features in MDIM 2.1 is estimated to be roughly one pixel (200 m), compared to 3 km for MDIM 2.0 released in 2001 and &gt;6 km for MDIM 1.0 released in 1991. In addition to relatively imprecise geodetic control, the previous mosaics were affected by changing definitions of cartographic parameters (such as the definition of zero longitude), resulting in an overall longitude shift of as much as 0.2° between the early MDIMs and other datasets. The new mosaic uses the most recent coordinate system definitions for Mars. These definitions have been widely adopted by NASA missions and other users of planetary data and are likely to remain in use for a decade or more. As a result, MDIM 2.1 not only registers precisely with data from current missions such as MGS and 2001 Mars Odyssey but will serve as an accurate basemap on which data from future missions can be plotted.</Abstract>
			<SRS>EPSG:4326</SRS>
			<FormatList>
				<Format current="1">image/png</Format>
			</FormatList>
			<StyleList>
						<Style>
							<Name>default</Name>
							<Title>default</Title>
							<LegendURL width="16" height="16">
								<OnlineResource xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://demo.cubewerx.com/demo/cubeserv/cubeserv.cgi?CONFIG=mars&amp;SERVICE=WMS&amp;VERSION=1.1.1&amp;REQUEST=GetLegendGraphic&amp;LAYER=OCEANIC%3AMARS_DATA&amp;FORMAT=image%2Fpng&amp;SIMPLE=TRUE"/>
							</LegendURL>
						</Style>
			</StyleList>
		</Layer>
		<Layer queryable="1" hidden="1">
			<Server service="OGC:WMS" version="1.1.1" title="OGC:WMS">
				<OnlineResource xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://demo.cubewerx.com/demo/cubeserv/cubeserv.cgi?CONFIG=mars"/>
			</Server>
						<Name>OCEANIC:MARS_DATA</Name>
						<Title>Oceanic</Title>
						<Abstract>The Blue Mars map is a 24bit colour image in Plate Carée Equirectangular projection, representing the surface of Mars in one possible aspect from billions of years ago, when parts of the surface where probably filled with water. A situation similar to the Earth with oceans.  BLUE MARS was completely done using Terragen and the Waterworks plugin. Topography and surface details matched with the "ieg0031t" MOLA dataset.</Abstract>
			<SRS>EPSG:4326</SRS>
			<FormatList>
				<Format current="1">image/png</Format>
			</FormatList>
			<StyleList>
						<Style>
							<Name>default</Name>
							<Title>default</Title>
							<LegendURL width="16" height="16">
								<OnlineResource xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://demo.cubewerx.com/demo/cubeserv/cubeserv.cgi?CONFIG=mars&amp;SERVICE=WMS&amp;VERSION=1.1.1&amp;REQUEST=GetLegendGraphic&amp;LAYER=OCEANIC%3AMARS_DATA&amp;FORMAT=image%2Fpng&amp;SIMPLE=TRUE"/>
							</LegendURL>
						</Style>
			</StyleList>
		</Layer>
		<Layer queryable="1" hidden="0">
			<Server service="OGC:WMS" version="1.1.1" title="OGC:WMS">
				<OnlineResource xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://demo.cubewerx.com/demo/cubeserv/cubeserv.cgi?CONFIG=mars"/>
			</Server>
			<Name>MARS_LANDINGS:MARS_DATA</Name>
			<Title>Mars Landings</Title>
			<SRS>EPSG:4326</SRS>
			<FormatList>
				<Format current="1">image/gif</Format>
			</FormatList>
			<StyleList>
				<Style current="1">
					<Name>default</Name>
					<Title>default</Title>
					<LegendURL width="16" height="16" format="image/gif">
						<OnlineResource xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://demo.cubewerx.com/demo/cubeserv/cubeserv.cgi?CONFIG=mars&amp;VERSION=1.1.1&amp;REQUEST=GetLegendGraphic&amp;LAYER=MARS_LANDINGS%3AMARS_DATA&amp;STYLE=icons&amp;FORMAT=image%2Fgif"/>
					</LegendURL>
				</Style>
			</StyleList>
		</Layer>
	</LayerList>
</ViewContext>
