<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
  <title>GeoServer Developer How To</title>

  <para>When adding your lastest, greatest ideas into the GeoServer framework
  there is one stop over point that most developement shares: the User.</para>

  <para>There are two places in which the User may interact with GeoServer:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>configuration files</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>user interface</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>This document provides a detailed walkthrough on how to add your own
  information to the GeoServer configuration system.</para>

  <para>A quick checklist for those that never read the whole document:</para>

  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Configuration files can be added to without problem</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>The new configuration information must be optional</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Write up a propsal to the email list for review/comment:</para>

      <programlisting>Be sure to include:
name: name of configuration information
description: what the information is needed for
xml fragment: example extention to an existing configuration file</programlisting>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Wait for a sanity check from a project lead, or at least a biz
      day.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Extend a configuraiton file</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Extend appropriate DTO class, along with XMLReader and XMLWriter</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Update appropriate class in global</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Update appropriate class in config, along with form and jsp</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>

  <para>Note duplication of information is never cool: if you have one watch
  you know what time it is, if you have two watches you are never quite sure.
  This is most often a problem with schema.xml. XMLSchema is so powerful, and
  so difficult to parse, that we often wish for an easier way.</para>

  <para>The GeoServer configuration system, is not so much a starting point
  for your GeoServer development as an ending point. Welcome to the final leg
  of your GeoServer developement, we thank you for your support.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Configuration Files</title>

    <para>GeoServer makes use of a series of xml files to store configuration
    information:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>services.xml:used to define the common GeoServer configuration
        options in addition to WFS and WMS services</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>catalog.xml: used to configure the data subsystem</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>info.xml (&#38; associated schema.xml): used to define which
        FeatureTypes are available through the data subsystem</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>One of your first chalanges will be to decide which xml file you
    option belongs in. Lets start by considering our example.</para>

    <para>Example Configuration issue from Jira:</para>

    <programlisting><emphasis role="bold">Jira Task:</emphasis> GEOS-58: Ability to turn off Transactions
<emphasis role="bold">Description:</emphasis>
Users have requested the ability to turn &#39;off&#39; transaction capabilities, so that users of their
WFS&#39;s can not modify their databases. I&#39;m not sure if this is in 1.2 yet or not, but we should
get the fix in there, and in a 1.1.1 bug fix release. It should be pretty easy to implement, just
have a configuration setting to turn it off, and transactions check with that global value before
letting a transaction go through. </programlisting>

    <para>This task is to do with the Web Feature Server Functionality of
    GeoServer. So we will want to work with the services.xml file and add an
    additional option to the wfs section.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Figure out how to Extend a Configuration File</title>

      <para>Extentions should allways be addative, and optional. We do not
      wish to break existing installations of GeoServer.</para>

      <para>For our example we will add a &#34;serviceLevel&#34; tag to the
      wfs section of services.xml. The OGC allows considerable varience in the
      capabilities of a Web Feature Server while still remaining complient
      with their specification.</para>

      <table>
        <title>Web Feature Server Complient Levels of Service</title>

        <tgroup cols="3">
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>OGC Complient</entry>

              <entry>Opperations</entry>

              <entry>Allowable value</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Basic Web Feature Server</entry>

              <entry>GetCapabilities DescribeFeatureType GetFeature</entry>

              <entry><literal>basic</literal></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Transaction Web Feature Server</entry>

              <entry>Transaction</entry>

              <entry>transactional</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Transaction WFS with Optional Locking</entry>

              <entry>LockFeature GetFeatureWithLock</entry>

              <entry>complete</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>Extension to services.xml for WFS Level of Service:</para>

      <programlisting>&#60;wfs&#62;
 ...
 &#60;serviceLevel&#62;Basic&#60;/serviceLevel
 ...
&#60;/wfs&#62;</programlisting>

      <para>There is almost a conflict here with the FeatureType configuration
      files, not all FeatureTypes are editable and as such will not allow the
      Transaction opperation. As noted in the GEOS-58 task an acceptable
      workaround is to restrict write access for the GeoServer at the
      DataStore level (this can be acomplished by changing file, or database
      permissions).</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Submit Idea to the Email Lists</title>

      <para>Next up we can submit our idea to the email list, the following
      email can serve as an example. Although it includes additional
      recomendations for the DTO and User Interface.</para>

      <para>Sample email:</para>

      <programlisting><emphasis>subject:</emphasis> Configuration proposal for Transactions control

Request for a new configuration information:
1) name: serviceLevel
2) requirement: needed to control level of WFS service (see GEOS-58
3) configuration file: service.xml
4) sample xml fragements:
&#60;wfs&#62;
 ...
 &#60;serviceLevel&#62;Basic&#60;/serviceLevel
 ...
&#60;/wfs&#62;

Where serviceLevel can be one of:

Basic
-----
Operations: GetCapabilities
           DescribeFeatureType
           GetFeature
OGC: Basic Web Feature Server

Transactional
-------------
Opperations: Transaction
OGC: Transactional Web Feature Server

Complete
--------
Opperations: LockFeature

5) DTO modifications: serviceType enum of Basic/Transaction/Complete
6) UI modifications: select drop down on the WFSCondig screen

For additional information See:
http://jira.codehaus.org/secure/ViewIssue.jspa?key=GEOS-93
http://jira.codehaus.org/secure/ViewIssue.jspa?key=GEOS-58 </programlisting>

      <para>And then we get to wait for Chris Holmes, or some other friendly
      GeoServer maintainer for approval. As long as you are simply extending a
      configuration file with optional content, we may as well go onto the
      next section while we wait.</para>

      <para>We just won&#39;t commit quite yet.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Extending XML Reader &#38; XML Writer</title>

      <para>Over to you David !</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>